<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on the 18th of April, 1692 at the funeral of the reverend Dr. Anthony Walker, late rector of Fyfield in the county of Essex, deceased by Josiah Woodward ...</title>
            <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12743976</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12743976</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on the 18th of April, 1692 at the funeral of the reverend Dr. Anthony Walker, late rector of Fyfield in the county of Essex, deceased by Josiah Woodward ...</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 7-29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathanael Ranew ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93188:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached On the 18th. of <hi>April,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>AT THE <hi>FUNERAL</hi> Of the Reverend Dr. <hi>ANTHONY WALKER,</hi> Late Rector of <hi>Fyfield</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Deceaſed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSIAH WOODWARD</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Popler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>NATHANAEL RANEW,</hi> at the <hi>King's Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93188:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93188:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Mourning Relations and Friends</hi> Of the Reverend Dr. <hi>ANTHONY WALKER,</hi> Lately Deceaſed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT muſt be look'd on as an Inſtance of your Affection to the Subject, rather than your eſteem of the management of it, that you have requeſted the Publication of it with ſuch an urgency, as Civil Reſpect could not deny: There being uſually in Mourners a kind of ſatisfaction in humouring their Grief, by viewing and reviewing any thing (though never ſo mean) that any way relates to a dear Friend taken from them. And thoſe who know any thing of my Sentiments in this Matter, will deem it no low inſtance of my Reſpect, that you ſo far gain the Aſcendant over me, as to induce me to yield to a thing ſo diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory
<pb facs="tcp:93188:3"/> to my ſelf, that I may contribute to your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. It being (as I often aſſured you) both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all my former Intentins, and contrary to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Inclinations, to commit theſe immature Thoughts to the <hi>Preſs,</hi> which I could not have Pardoned my ſelf for delivering in the Pulpit before ſuch an Audience, had I had leiſure ſuitable to the Solemn Occaſion.</p>
            <p>But your Requeſt being granted, I only beg of God that it may improve any Teachable Mind and Honeſt Heart. For, as for ſuch as are of another Temper; What can either pleaſe or profit them? To whom even our Sacred Religion it ſelf is unſavoury, and all ſerious thoughts about another World, a ſort of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly-Madneſs. Oh! May the God of Truth and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs vouchſafe a ſpeedy ſtop to the rapid Floods of ungodlineſs, by which we are almoſt overwhelm'd even to Deſtruction. To contribute towards which, it is a very ſmall thing to hazzard our Reputation amongſt the Enemies of Serious Religion: For he that has the Temper of that Bleſſed Saviour and Religion that we profeſs, will not think his Life dear, if by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of it he could be Inſtrumental to ſtop up the way of ſuch as haſten to Deſtruction: which deſirable end may it pleaſe the All-governing God, to work out of what is here laid before you, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all Sincere Affection and Reſpect, J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93188:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON <hi>Preached at the funeral of</hi> Dr. <hi>ANTHONY WALKER.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Zech. 1. 5.</bibl>
               <q>The Prophets, do they live for ever?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is not without deep Grief that I enter upon this Mournful Employment aſſign'd me by the Reverend Perſon whoſe Remains lie before us. Every thought of it is afflicting, and I am ſure to find here many Partners in my Sorrows; which deplorable Conjunction of our Grief would make it too exorbitant; did we not conſider, that it would be a Violating, rather than a Solemnizing of our Worthy Friend's <hi>Funerals,</hi> to be ſorry as Men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Hope.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93188:4"/>
            <p>And indeed as 'twas never God's Will that good Men (at leaſt ſince the Fall) ſhould have their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs here: So we act but an unkind part, when we too much grudge and grieve, that they are aſcended above Sin and Mortality. So that I ſhall hope, The Sorrow of this Mournful Solemnity may be much Extenuated, and in ſome meaſure Sanctified; by conſidering, That as the Death of the beſt is the uſual courſe of that Providence which admits no Error, ſo it is none of the unkindeſt of God's Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations to his Servants, to put an end to the weary ſteps of their Pilgrimage. 'Tis well for the Prophets that they are not to live here for ever.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prophet</hi> indeed puts it to the <hi>Queſtion</hi> in the <hi>Text;</hi> yet ſo as to imply that there was no <hi>Queſtion</hi> to be made of it: ſince every body ſaw that the <hi>Prophets</hi> did not live for ever here. As 'tis ſaid, (<hi>John 8. 53.) Abraham</hi> is dead, and the <hi>Prophets</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 8. 53.</note> are dead They fall ſick and die as other Mortals, though with better Hope, more chearful Hearts, and greater fitneſs for their Change than the Vain and Vicious part of the World.</p>
            <p>That which ocaſioned the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> to make mention of the Mortality of his Brethren the <hi>Prophets,</hi> was to make it a motive to the Hearers of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> to Repent and Reform ſpeedily accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Doctrine. As though he had ſaid, <q>You had beſt improve your ſelves now by the Miniſtry of the <hi>Prophets:</hi> They are as Mortal as your ſelves; and your incorrigibleneſs may make the Death of the <hi>Prophets</hi> a Judicial ſtroak upon your ſelves.</q> Wherefore walk whilſt you have the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93188:4"/> Light, the Night cometh when none can work. And when God draws his <hi>Noahs</hi> and <hi>Lots</hi> out of a place, Woe be to thoſe that remain behind. The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments foretold by the <hi>Prophets</hi> uſually attend their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture: as it follows (<hi>verſe 6.) But my Words and my Statutes which I Commanded my Servants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, did they not take hold of your Fathers?</hi> That is, was not the Sanction of my Holy Statutes veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Execution of the Penalties Decreed to the breach of them? Did not the Deſolation fore-told by the <hi>Prophets</hi> come upon your disbelieving <hi>Fore-Fathers?</hi> You canno but confeſs they did, and that the Prediction proceeded to its accompliſhment, tho' the <hi>Oracle</hi> ceaſed.</p>
            <p>Now the Duty and Office of a <hi>Prophet</hi> of old, bears a ſubſtantial Analogy with that of Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Miniſters now: Both had a Divine Commiſſion to inſtruct People in the Mind and Will of God. But with this difference; The <hi>Prophets</hi> of old, ſpake by immediate and extraordinary Revelation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God: Whereas God's Miniſters now, have a Written and Eſtabliſhed Rule by which they teach, even that perfect Syſtem of Doctrine in our <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> which fully contains the Faith once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints: To which to preſume to add, is Enthuſiaſtick Deluſion, as to diminiſh from it is Sacrilegious Violence. All deviation from it on the right hand or on the left, being Falſhood and Folly. But the End and Aim of God's Miniſters the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> of old, and his Miniſters the Paſtors now is the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> to bring Men to the Saving Knowledge of God in Jeſus Chriſt, and a filial Submiſſion to his Sacred Will. Upon which account we find the Holy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93188:5"/> Ghoſt uſing the words Propheſying and Preaching as Synonymous Terms for the ſame thing. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 3. and again <hi>verſe</hi> 24.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 3. and 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as God then did not diſcover future Events to Men, only to gratifie their Childiſh Ears with Novels, but to affect their Hearts and transform their Lives. So, is not the Chriſtian Religion given us to be the <hi>Object</hi> of a curious Speculation, but to be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our careful and Conſcientious Practice. So then, the Holy Office of a <hi>Prophet</hi> under the Law and a <hi>Pastor</hi> under the Goſpel being the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; the words of the <hi>Text</hi> will naturally apply themſelves to our preſent occaſion, and ſhew us, that neither the Sacred Dignity of the <hi>Miniſterial Office,</hi> nor the Faithfulleſt diſcharge of it, can be any Protection from Death.</p>
            <p>This is ſad News to this dark World, That the Lights of it will ſo ſoon be put out. And this, alas! is the ſad cauſe of the preſent Mourning and Grief of this place. Death hath cloſed thoſe Compaſſionate Hands which ſo often Adminiſtred to your Wants, and ended that Fatherly Care which ſo peculiarly conſulted the Intereſts of your particular Perſons and Families. And what's the ſaddeſt of all, alas! That Mouth which ſo often and ſo ſervently treated of the Great Things of God's Law in your Ears, is now lock'd up in perfect ſilence till the Reſurrection. The <hi>Prophets</hi> are Mortals, <hi>They do not live for ever.</hi> So that the obſervable point in which the words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us, is,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93188:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That the greatest Eminency in the Church below,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prop.</note> 
               <hi>is no exemption from the Mortality common to Men.</hi> The <hi>Prophets</hi> are not <hi>Angels</hi> by Nature, though they are <hi>Angels</hi> by Office, as they are term'd (<hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 1.) as being the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of God to the <hi>Churches,</hi> and bringing them Tidings from Heaven. But their Breath is in their Noſtrils, and is as ſoon blown out as other Mens: The <hi>Text</hi> ſuggeſts, That the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets do not live for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, the Faithful ſhall in the beſt ſenſe live for ever: For our Bleſſed Saviour (<hi>The Truth and the Life</hi>) has promiſed that ſuch as <hi>believe in him ſhall never</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 11. 26.</note> 
               <hi>die,</hi> (John 11. 26.) They ſhall live for ever in his Preſence and Kingdom. So that if the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> ſhould put the <hi>Queſtion</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> as a Scoff or Taunt; The words are anſwerable in the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative. The <hi>Prophets</hi> do and will live for ever in Beatifick Glory. They are not capable of Diſeaſes or<note place="margin">Revel. 21. 4.</note> Death there, <hi>Rev. 21. 4. There is no more Death nor Sorrow, nor Crying; neither ſhall there be any more Pain.</hi> The Holy <hi>Prophets</hi> may be here excruciated with the grinding Pains of the <hi>Stone,</hi> and <hi>Gout</hi> and <hi>Cholick,</hi> and other acute Diſtempers. But when once they put off their Corruptible, all's well. All Humane Maladies are driven away by the Glorious Preſence of God, as Shadows when there is nothing to interpoſe betwixt them and the <hi>Sun.</hi> So that it is very happy for the Faithful Servants of God, that they are ſo ſoon to remove from this State of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Diſcord, and Sin and Miſery.</p>
            <p>And indeed, Eminency of Grace is ſo far from being a Protection from Death, that it is often a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93188:6"/> Token of ſhort Life. The higher we grow in Grace, the nearer we approach to Glory. <hi>Enoch</hi> walked a Heavenly pace, and God took him ſpeedily to that place for which he was fit. The Church here is but as an under-School to fit us for the Church above; and when the Maſter ſees Men ſuch Proficients in Grace as to be fit for Glory, he removes them; and then they throw by their Mortal Fleſh, as graduates Shift the Habits of their Minor-State. This is that Perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Change which all the <hi>Prophets</hi> (except <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi>) and all the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> underwent. For though ſome thought that St. <hi>John</hi> was exempted from Death, and ſome vain People would yet perſwade us, That he is even to this day walking about yet we find he did not think ſo himſelf: Nor did our Saviour ever ſay, he ſhould not die: as<note place="margin">John 21. 23.</note> we read (<hi>John</hi> 21. 23.)</p>
            <p>The extravagant pretence of the <hi>Wandering Jew</hi> not many years ſince, was ſomething like this, who confidently affirm'd that he kept the door of the Hall where our Bleſſed Saviour was condemned at the time of his Trial before <hi>Pilate:</hi> And that Chriſt for ſome roughneſs of carriage towards him, deſtin'd him to live till his coming to Judgment: and that he had been a <hi>Pilgrim</hi> in all parts of the World ever ſince, and been an Eye-witneſs to the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the greateſt Tranſactions of the World ever ſince. This I ſay, was too palpable an Impoſtor (or rather Madneſs) to deceive any but ſuch as were as Brain-ſick as himſelf.</p>
            <p>Let me ſpeak freely (ſays St. <hi>Peter</hi>) of the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch David, That he is both dead and buried; and his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93188:6"/> Sepulcre is with us unto this day,</hi> Acts 2. 29. So Great a Progenitor and ſo Eminent a Type of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> was compelled to yield to the neceſſary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays and Deceaſe of Natural Life. His Lamp burnt long indeed, and in a leiſurely manner conſum'd the Vital Moiſture and Warmth (thoſe <hi>Stamina Vitae</hi>) but it was at laſt extinguiſh'd, or rather went out of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee the ſcope of the Doctrine in the Text illuſtrated. That the greateſt Eminency in God's Church here, is no exemption from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mortality. Which great Truth I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to improve and apply theſe two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shewing how the Goodneſs and Wiſdom of God's Providence, appears in the Deaths of good Men, particularly of Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What uſe both Miniſters and People ought to make of this Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>I begin to ſhew that the Goodneſs and Wiſdom of God is ſeen in a peculiar manner in the Death of Faithful Miniſters: which may turn our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the ſeverity of God's Providences into Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and Praiſe of the infinite Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which directed and diſpenſed them. For,</p>
            <p>1. The Graciouſneſs of God's Providence appears in the Death of Faithful Miniſters, in that God hereby gives them reſt from their Labours. The Laborious and Stedfaſt Servants of God are encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd by a Voice from Heaven to go on cheerfully in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93188:7"/> their preſent Labours in hope of the reſt to come. <hi>Rev. 14. 13. Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 14. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, from henceforth;</hi> yea, <hi>ſaith the Spirit, That they may reſt from their Labours.</hi> Now, a Faithful Miniſter is not only a Labourer, but a Labourer in Harveſt (<hi>Matth.</hi> 9. 38.) a time in which every one<note place="margin">Matth, 9. 38.</note> puts out his ſtrength to the utmoſt. We are gathering up the Wheat in Chriſt's Field; and there are many Adverſaries interrupting and retarding our Work. The envious <hi>Legions</hi> of Darkneſs are deluding and deſtroying of multitudes; and what is worſe, too many love to have it ſo. We ſee their pernicious ways and who leads them on in them, yet all our Calls and Cries in their Ears will not make them conſider and amend; they love the works of Darkneſs, and ſeem to value Temptations to Deſtruction. This is that which makes our Labours very Afflictive; as it was at once the Grief and Anger of our Supreme Paſtor in the days of his Fleſh (<hi>Mark 3. 5.) He look'd round</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 3. 5.</note> 
               <hi>about on them with Anger, being griev'd for the hardneſs of their Hearts.</hi> Alas, too great a part of our uſual Audience are no more affected with the great Promiſes and Threatnings of God's Book, than if we ſpake to the Graves of thoſe who have been long dead. However, 'tis our Great Maſter's Will that we Labour in Seaſon and out of Seaſon. And the Laborious Miniſter who ſpends and is ſpent in God's Service, ſhall have his <hi>Quietus</hi> very ſpeedily. The <hi>Watch-man</hi> ſhall not ſtand <hi>Centinel</hi> long, ſome Diſeaſe or ſome other means will call him off his Watch; and then every Act of his careful Induſtry and Zeal for God, ſhall be infinitely Rewarded.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93188:7"/>
            <p>Of many a Faithful <hi>Paſtor</hi> it may be ſaid, as <hi>Jacob</hi> expreſs'd himſelf concerning the reſtleſs Fatigue he underwent in ſecuring <hi>Laban</hi>'s Flock. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 40.<note place="margin">Gen. 31. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Thus I was, in the day the Drought conſumed me and the Froſt by night, and my ſleep departed from mine Eyes.</hi> The difficulty of our Work will give us ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny laborious days; and our too little ſucceſs may well bring upon us many reſtleſs nights. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the utmoſt Application and Earneſtneſs of our Head and Heart day and night is little enough, in order to finiſh our courſe with Joy. For when we conſider the Immortality of the Souls under our care; and that Chriſt purchaſed them with his own Blood; And that we are plac'd by the Great God as <hi>Overſeers</hi> of them; And finally, That the guilt of ſo deplorable a Ruine as the infinite Miſery of an everlaſting Soul will be imputable to us, if through our negligence it miſcarries: I ſay, when we are du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of theſe tremendous things, we cannot think any pains too great to ſave a Soul from Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, Eternal Torment: nor to ſpend a few drops of ſweat in labouring to pull Men out of the Claws of the <hi>Devil,</hi> when for this very thing our Bleſſed Lord ſhed Showers of his Blood. Theſe Thoughts will make every tender <hi>Paſtor</hi> put himſelf out to the utmoſt. And the leſs reſt we take here, the ſweeter will be our everlaſting repoſe above. The cool Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Death draws on when the Limbs of the weary ſhall be at reſt, and ſhall never be diſturb'd more. The ſame propitious Hand which wipes away the Tears from the Eyes of the diſconſolate Chriſtian, will wipe away the Sweat from the Brows of the Painful. And then there's a full end of their Labours
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93188:8"/> and Sorrows. No more hard Hearts to grieve their tender Bowels; no more filthy Converſations to vex their Righteous Souls. But undiſturbed Joys abound even to exultation for evermore.</p>
            <p>This then is an Expreſſion of God's infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Compaſſion to his Faithful Miniſters, in that the infliction of Death is a diſmiſſion from their Labours. Which will ſurther appear,</p>
            <p>2. In that by Death they are ſecured from the Malice of their Enemies. For 'tis no new thing that the moſt inoffenſive life ſhould meet with Enmity from the World. We muſt not think to fare better than our Maſter, who was thus Treated all his life long; and being brought to his Death by the ſame malicious Enmity of wicked Men, he told his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers what they muſt expect from this evil World. <hi>John</hi> 15. 21. The Diſpoſitions, and Intereſts, and<note place="margin">John 15. 21.</note> Ways of good and bad Men are diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite; and when there's ſuch a Conſtitutional diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Inclinations, and thwarting of Roads, there are like to be many differences; and then 'tis eaſie to ſay who will be greateſt ſufferers, either the few harmleſs <hi>Pilgrims</hi> that are ſo far from doing an Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that they would not return one to gain the whole World: Or a numerous Company of Paſſionate, Proud, Envious, and Violent Men who take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in unrighteouſneſs. From ſome of theſe, every one that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt expect at ſome time or other to ſuffer Tribulation in ſome meaſure; as both our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> have fore-told, and as their own Sufferings fore-ſhew'd.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93188:8"/>
            <p>Yet one would indeed have thought, that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God had ſufficiently ſecured his <hi>Prophets</hi> from Violence; when he had given ſuch a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Charge that they ſhould do his <hi>Prophets no harm,</hi> Pſal. 105. 15. And when <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Paſſion<note place="margin">Pſal. 105. 15.</note> had tranſported him ſo far beyond the meaſures of Equity, as to ſtretch forth his hand againſt a <hi>Prophet</hi> of the Lord, his injurious Arm was inſtantly wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd, ſo that he could not pull it in to him again, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. 4. So that God <hi>reprov'd even Kings for</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>their ſakes.</hi> And on the other ſide, who could have thought but that every Body would have been kind and obliging to the <hi>Prophets,</hi> when God had promis'd, That ſo ſmall a kindneſs as <hi>a Cup of cold water given to a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhould not be unrewarded,</hi> Matth. 10. 42. Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Matth. 10. 42.</note> withall, That this was a promiſe made by that infinite Remunerator, who gives whole Cities for the improvement of ſome petty Pounds (<hi>Luke</hi> 19.<note place="margin">Luke 19. 17.</note> 17.) Yet, alas! notwithſtanding the Great God had both promis'd and threatned ſo highly in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his <hi>Prophets;</hi> through what Vollies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and Defiles of Injuries did they uſually run their Courſe? And through what painful and bloody Deaths did the moſt of them make their entrance into Glory? <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is ſaid to be ſawn aſunder; <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to be ſtoned to Death; <hi>Ezechiel</hi> is reported to be ſlain by the Captain of the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Babylon; Amos</hi> his Brains beaten out by <hi>Amaſias</hi> the Idolatrous <hi>Prieſt</hi> of <hi>Bethel. Micah</hi>'s Neck broken by <hi>Joram</hi> the Son of <hi>Ahab.</hi> And (to name no more) <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah,</hi> the Pen-man of the words of the <hi>Text,</hi> is ſuppos'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93188:9"/> to be the <hi>Prophet</hi> of whom our Bleſſed Saviour ſays, He was <hi>ſlain betwixt the Porch and the Altar, (Matth.</hi> 23. 35.) There being no other <hi>Zecharias</hi> the Son of<note place="margin">Matth. 23. 35.</note> 
               <hi>Barachias</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſave this <hi>Prophet</hi> whoſe Genealogy is thus Recorded, <hi>Zech. 1. 1. In the Eighth Month came the Word of the Lord to Zechariah the Son of Barachiah,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Many more Inſtances of this Nature are Collected by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in his Account of the Lives of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> And if we look into that Sacred Book which ought to be in our Hands every day, we ſhall there find that the Holy <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſped no better. And the Hiſtories of thoſe times aſſure us, That hardly any one of them died otherwiſe than by a violent Death; ſome were Crucify'd, ſome Ston'd, ſome ſlain with the Sword, others had their Brains beat out with Clubs. In ſo much, that one of them Writes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 9.</note> 4. 9. God ſeems to have ſent out us the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> laſt, as Men appointed to be ſlain. A ſort of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn Squadrons who made the firſt Effort againſt the Powerful Patrons of Sin, and Attact Wickedneſs ſeated in high places, who ſoon ſhew'd their Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wrath againſt ſuch as durſt diſturb their haughty Luſts. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>'s Faithful Reproof of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Adultery, coſt him his Head: the <hi>Jewiſh Sanhedrim</hi> being reproov'd by St. <hi>Stephen</hi> for their blood-guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they gnaſh upon him with their Teeth as if they'd worry him; as indeed they ſoon did, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 54.<note place="margin">Acts 7. 54.</note> And ſome of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Hearers became his <hi>Enemies, becauſe he told them the Truth,</hi> (Gal. 4. 16.)<note place="margin">Gal. 4. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93188:9"/>
            <p>But the Meſſengers of God find wellcome above when they meet with none on Earth. God calls them away as an affronted <hi>Prince</hi> calls away his <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> from a Foreign Court, not in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to his Servant, but in Anger to the place he leaves.</p>
            <p>3. The great wiſdom and awful Righteouſneſs of God's Providence appears in the Death of Faithful Miniſters, in that this is a means of bringing them to render an Account of their Ambaſſy at the Court of Heaven. <hi>They watch for your Souls</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul) as they that muſt give an Account,</hi> Heb. 13. 17. We<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 17.</note> muſt at laſt declare before the Judge of the World; How faithfully we have promulged the Will of God? How impartially we have reproved Sin? How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly we have watch'd over Souls? And with what ſerious earneſtneſs we have further'd their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: God grant that this may be to our Comfort and not Confuſion. We are God's <hi>Leiger-Ambaſſadors</hi> in our ſeveral <hi>Pariſhes;</hi> and muſt expect to be call'd home ere long to make Report, how we have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiated the grand Intereſts of our Maſter's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? And then (ſays the <hi>Prophet) Such as have turn'd many to Righteouſneſs ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12. 3.</p>
            <p>4. The Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God appears in the Deaths of Faithful Miniſters, in that their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are likely to be much awaken'd by, and confirm'd in, the Truths of God atteſted and apply'd by their dying Lips. 'Tis the Argument of <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93188:10"/> 
               <hi>Apology</hi> for the Chriſtians; <q>That of all the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them that were put to Death, yet none of them died without a Zealous Confeſſion of the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion, affirming with their laſt Breath, That it was the Wiſdom and Power of God to Salvation: So that uſually very numerous Converſions were made by the conſtancy of their Dying Confeſſions.</q> At Death, even the vaineſt of Men are uſually ſerious: With how much greater weight then, will every Sentence of good Men drop from their dying Lips? Their Faith is almoſt Viſion. So that they may be ſaid to ſtand on the brink of the other World, and ſeeing the great things there, they turn about to acquaint the ſtanders-by, what a Righteous Judge there is in the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing World! What an All-ſufficient Saviour! What a Beatifick Paradiſe, where infinite Vollies of <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs,</hi> and Triumphant <hi>Joys</hi> abound for evermore! And finally, what a tremendous <hi>Tophet</hi> is prepared, where the Worm never dies, and the Fire is never quenched. Thus, methinks, the dying Servants of God may (like <hi>Sampſon</hi>) ſlay more of God's Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at their Death, than in their whole Life.</p>
            <p>And in theſe laſt Efforts of Devout Men againſt Impiety: I dare aſſure the People of this place, That their Deceaſed <hi>Paſtor</hi> would have been very earneſt and very copious: Had it not pleaſed God, that he ſhould ſo ſuddenly, and at ſuch a diſtance be deprived of his precious Life. But the Will of God is ever Adorable. That thought muſt ſtifle all the Complaints which our wounded Affections are apt to make in ſuch Trials: And we muſt ever own
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93188:10"/> God's Sovereign Providence not only with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Silence, but entire Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>5. And laſtly, The Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God's Providence appears in the Deaths of Faithful <hi>Pastors;</hi> in that hereby opportunity is adminiſtred to others of God's Witneſſes to come and confirm the ſame Truths.</p>
            <p>God ſends <hi>Prophet</hi> after <hi>Prophet, Miniſter</hi> after <hi>Miniſter, riſing early and ſending them,</hi> (Jer. 44. 4.)<note place="margin">Jer. 44. 4.</note> As it were Storming a ſturdy Heart by freſh aſſaults, that ſo being encompaſſed with ſo great an Army of <hi>Champions</hi> Valiant for the <hi>Truth,</hi> the moſt obſtinate ſinner might think of Surrender: eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that all theſe will be Witneſſes for us or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee what excellent ends an All-Wiſe and All-Good Providence brings about even in thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations which we think the moſt fore and ſevere: and therefore we have reaſon to ſay, when the good Hand of God takes away, as well as when it gives, <hi>Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Les us now apply all, as it was propoſed, Firſt, to <hi>Miniſters</hi> themſelves. And, Secondly, to their <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Firſt, to <hi>Miniſters</hi> themſelves. If no Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in God's Church can ſecure us from Death and Judgment, (for the <hi>Prophets cannot live for ever</hi> here) Let us then, as we ſhall anſwer it to the Great God, diſcharge the Duties of our Sacred Office with all poſſible diligence and exactneſs. We have but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93188:11"/> time to do a great deal of difficult work. We have the dark minds of Men (under God) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten: Hearts of Stone to ſoften and warm: many a ſtray Sheep to reduce: and many a Prey to ſnatch out of the <hi>Devil</hi>'s Teeth, and to bring into Chriſt's Fold. Ah! What a difficult Task has that Shepherd, who has a numerous Flock to over-look, and ſees Wolves breaking in on every ſide, and carrying away a great part of his Flock: (the reſt alſo being apt to ſtraggle and run into Snares) and perhaps he finds little aſſiſtance from others, but much diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. This alas! is our very Caſe; and except we put out our utmoſt Diligence and Courage, we may probably loſe many a Soul that might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have been ſaved. For, the <hi>Devil</hi> is the more diligent in deceiving and deſtroying, as knowing, <hi>He has but a ſhort time</hi> (Revel. 12. 12.) And<note place="margin">Revel. 12. 12.</note> except we are moved by the ſame conſideration, what Ravage will the Deſtroyer make? and 'twill be very ſaid, if through our ſloath or ſin any Soul be loſt for which Chriſt died. Let us then labour to ſtrengthen the weak Chriſtian, and to eſtabliſh the wavering, and to reſtore the lapſed: and even the beſt will need a ſhare in our Conduct, but none more than the Tempted, the Doubtful, and the Dying. Oh! what work is here for a frail Mortal Man in the due diſcharge of his Miniſterial Vows! We may well ſay, <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe mighty things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May the Thoughts of theſe Difficulties then add an edge to our Induſtry; and ſince we have but a little time here, let us advance our Maſter's Work and Intereſt with all our might. This is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93188:11"/> thing we have to mind, and ought to be upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in our Mind and Heart day and night. It was a moving conſideration to our Bleſſed Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to think that he had but a little time to be in this World; (<hi>John 9. 4.) I muſt work the works of</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 9. 4.</note> 
               <hi>him that ſent me, whilſt it's day, the night cometh when no Man can work.</hi> And with what Zeal did St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhort and ſtir up the Affections of his People? <hi>Knowing</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that I muſt ſhortly put off this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 14. And Oh! That this weighty<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 14.</note> Thought filled our Heart every time we either ſpake to the Great God, or to Men in his Name. What Fervour would it give to our Prayers, and what Life to our Sermons?</p>
            <p>And in theſe things, I do not queſtion but the Life of this our <hi>Reverend Brother</hi> Deceaſed, afforded many Inſtances in which he deſerved to be our Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern. But his Modeſty ſeems to deſign that a <hi>Veil</hi> ſhould be drawn over him at his <hi>Funeral;</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting me to this Office, who have been too lately of his Acquaintance. In this indeed he gives a Juſt Reproof to a Vanity too common with Men, who deſire a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> at their <hi>Funeral</hi> rather than a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which is rather to Inſtruct the Living than Applaud the Dead.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt Piety and Prudence values not the admiring Eyes and Tongues of the World, content to have their Hearts and Ways approved of an Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient God. Yet even this Affectation of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment uſually draws Men to a more careful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection. And therefore I cannot but again lament
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93188:12"/> the ſhortneſs of my Acquaintance with ſo Valuable and Deſirable a Friend. 'Tis not much above two years, ſince I had the opportunity (though on a ſad occaſion) of the firſt Diſcourſe I ever had with him: which was ſeconded by one of the moſt condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and kind Acts of Friendſhip on his part, that I ever met with. And ſo was he pleaſed to continue a ſort of Friendly Correſpondence, which ſeem'd to be made up of the Kindneſs of a Father temper'd with the Familiarity of a Brother; though our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Habitation too much interrupted the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Acquaintance. So that I here lament the Death of a moſt Affectionate and Generous Friend; Acting rather like a near Relation, than a new Acquaintance, and am now never more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the benefits of his endearing and edifying Society upon Earth.</p>
            <p>In this particular of his obliging Amity, I know ſuch as had the Happineſs to be Related to him, will even paſſionately concurr with me in their Laments for ſo ſenſible a loſs. Indeed this lower World has nothing in it ſo valuable as an entire Friend, the ſweet multiplier of our Joys, and divider of our Sorrows. But whilſt we are admiring our Happineſs, and think of building <hi>Tabernacles</hi> for our deſired Companions; a Cloud over-ſhadows the beloved <hi>Object,</hi> and we are left in Sorrow and Darkneſs. In which Caſe our Wiſdom lies in labouring to aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Regions of Bliſs above, where Love never ceaſes, nor is ſo much as pall'd by Death or Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93188:12"/>
            <p>This will alſo be the beſt uſe that we who are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to him by Office, can make of his <hi>Deceaſe,</hi> viz. To ſee in him our Neighbourhood to the Grave: And to endeavour that all the Piety, Charity, and Sobriety, and whatever elſe was Praiſe-worthy and of good Report, that was conſpicuous in him, may not be laid in the Grave with him but ſurvive in us. And ſince he was longer known to many of you than me: I muſt requeſt, That your own Obſervation may be the <hi>Monitor</hi> of your imitation of all things worthy of it. Wherefore,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whatever Pious and Prudent Zeal for God appeared in his Prayers, Sermons, Catechiſing, and familiar Diſcourſes: Let us Tranſcribe and Copy it. For except we are lively in our Affections our ſelves, we are not like to raiſe the Affections of others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whatever induſtry in particular and private Inſtruction and Converſion of Souls has been obſerved in our <hi>Reverend Brother,</hi> let us alſo follow the good Precedent. For not only the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Practice, but the Nature of our important work, ſhould prompt us to act the part of thoſe careful <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> who make particular Viſits to the Houſes and Beds of their Patients. For, the ſame Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will not be proper to all: and a particular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation is ever the moſt cloſe and powerful, which is of conſtant uſe to our People in their Health, but is chiefly neceſſary when they are viſited with Sickneſs, they being then warn'd of God to prepare for another World.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93188:13"/>
            <p>Thirdly, In whatever Acts of Bounty and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty this Reverend Perſon has given us a good Example, let us induſtriouſly follow it. For by the Dole of a ſmall <hi>Alms</hi> we may perhaps open the Heart of ſome poor Perſon to receive our Doctrine, and ſo may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to their Immortal Happineſs as well as their preſent Subſiſtence. 'Tis true we cannot (many of us in our low Sphere) adequate the Bounty of this tender Father of the Poor, either in the beneficent Diſtributions he made in his Life, or the Annual Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Rents which he bequeathed at his Death. Nor may we have ſuch <hi>Noble Almoners</hi> of our Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as from the Mouth of an Honourable. Lady I am aſſured, he had: Yet let us freely give of the Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which God vouchſafes us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In what Inſtances ſo ever he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Worthy Pattern of Chriſtian Moderation, and of general Love to all good Men, let us tread in the ſteps of his <hi>Chriſtian Catholiciſm.</hi> For why ſhould not we ſhew favour to ſuch as God favours? Or how can we be ſhy of the Company of ſuch, as God will vouchſafe to receive into his Kingdom? Difference in immaterial Opinions ſhould not divide the Hearts of ſuch as agree in the ſame Faith and Goſpel. And 'tis certain, the Flames of our Love may probably melt ſuch as the Flames of Wrath will very probably harden. 'Tis indeed a ſore Grief that there's no Healing: And I do not ſee, how on the one hand ſuch as do not condeſcend as far as they can: or on the other hand, how ſuch as do not comply as far as they can in order to a Bleſſed Union, (ſo conducive
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93188:13"/> to our Happineſs in both Worlds) will anſwer their affected ſtiffneſs before the <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> before whom we muſt all are long appear in Judgment.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Whatever Inſtances of a Pious Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our Reverend Friend has left us, let us be his Followers as far as he was a Follower of Chriſt: For when all is done, a Holy Life is the Life of all we do. And without this, a Miniſter is a ſad mixture of Contradictions. A very ſtrange Builder, who really pulls down what he pretends to build up.</p>
            <p>And ſo I turn me from ſuch as are Brethren to this Reverend Perſon by Office, to ſuch as were the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his Doctrine and the <hi>Objects</hi> of his Care.</p>
            <p>And here I know, you can better tell me than I you, what a ſerious Reprover of ſin and ſervent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate for Piety, is now taken away from you. But let me intreat you to do this Honour to his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>viz.</hi> To make the World ſee the Power of your Preachers Sermons in the unblamableneſs of your Converſations. Without this, your Praiſing of him with your Lips will appear a fullſome piece of Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or rather a downright Detraction; For the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of wicked Men is Defamatory. And Oh! With what confuſion of Face will you meet your Paſtor before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, if you then appear in the guilt of thoſe ſins, which he had been ſo long and ſo affectionately preſſing you to forſake?</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93188:14"/>
            <p>Let me then here ſpeak to ſuch as are young, that they ſeriouſly mind thoſe inſtructions which they have learnt from the Mouth of their <hi>Grave Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſt.</hi> May his Sage Counſels abide by you even to old age; which will be much Adorned and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by your early Piety. Wherefore ſee that ye convince a diſſolute Age, that Youth is as capable of Serious Religion as the Hoary Head; by which you will anſwer the end of your Worthy Paſtors Erecting and endowing a <hi>School</hi> for your Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>And as for ſuch of his Pariſhioners as are Aged: who have lived, ſome Thirty, ſome Forty years under ſo Beneficial a Miniſtry. Oh! Think, what vaſt Accounts you have to make to God, who will ſoon require at your hands the improvement of your many <hi>Talents.</hi> What Proficiency then and Profit have you made by the many awakening Sermons and Expoſtulations you have heard? Has your Fruit been anſwerable to your Tillage? Can you not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the time when your Hearts have been ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly touch'd and warm'd by his Doctrine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved for the ways of God? Be ye then ſtedfaſt and reſolute in all Chriſtian Duty, and Conſcientious in the diſcharge of your Vows. God lays it to the Charge of the incorrigible <hi>Jews,</hi> that they remained rough and unpoliſht notwithſtanding he had <hi>hewen them by his Servants the Prophets,</hi> (Hoſ. 6. 5.) It ſeems they were ſo hardened, that all the ſtroaks of their Miniſters level'd at their Luſts, could not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from 'em. May no ſhare of this fault ever be laid to your Charge.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93188:14"/>
            <p>If you have been ſuch ill Husbands for your Souls, as not to Record his edifying Sermons, yet his Care has left a ſtanding warning to you and to the World. <hi>Not to deferr your Repentance,</hi> and to haſten your Peace with God: which eſſential part of Wiſdom, I pray God encline us all to purſue and practiſe.</p>
            <p>I muſt now conclude my Mournful Subject, in which my Affection would carry me on, and my weighty Subject would bear me out: But I ſhould be injurious to ſuch, whoſe Affection to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Friend has brought them far from their Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore Pray, That as God calls home ſome of his Faithful Servants, ſo he would be pleaſed to raiſe up others in their room: particularly to the ſupply of this place, which has now ſuſtain'd ſuch a Loſs. May the great <hi>Shepherd</hi> of the <hi>Sheep,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Faithful <hi>Pastors</hi> to ſuch as enjoy ſo great a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: And vouchſafe ſuch to all places that want 'em. That the whole Church of God may flouriſh (particularly in theſe Nations) not only in our days, but till the Conſummation of all things.</p>
            <p>Which God of his infinite Mercy grant, through Jeſus Chriſt our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:93188:15"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>NATHANAEL RANEW,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PRactical Preparation for Death, the Interest and Wiſdom of Chriſtians the Folly and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe that are negligent therein. The great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of a life ſpent in a daily preparation for our latter end; with Motives and Directions for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof. Recommended as proper to be given at Funerals. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Glory and Happineſs of the Saints in Heaven: Or a Diſcourſe concerning the Bleſſed State of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous after Death. With Motives and Encouragements unto all Chriſtians to ſecure to themſelves an Intereſt therein. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Virtuous Woman,</hi> or the Life of <hi>Mary</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Warwick.</hi> With ſome of her Ladiſhips Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reflections on ſeveral Scriptures, and Meditations on ſeveral Subjects. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy Life of Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Walker,</hi> late Wife of Dr. <hi>Anthony Walker. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Evil and Danger of <hi>Procraſtination,</hi> or delaying our <hi>Repentance,</hi> in four Funeral <hi>Sermons,</hi> by <hi>Anthony Walker.</hi> Twelves.</p>
            <p>An Expoſition on the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> and <hi>Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments;</hi> with ſeveral <hi>Sermons</hi> on divers Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. By <hi>Ezekiel Hopkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-derry. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
